# Douglas Waugh - Senior Developer

## **Contact Details**

Mobile phone number: 07863546306

Email address: douglas.waugh.e3@gmail.com

Postal address: 8 Brighton Avenue, London, E17 7NE

## Introduction

## **Development Methodology**

I write easy to understand, easy to change code that works. I focus on delivering the highest value to the business in the shortest possible time.

In order to do this I utilise several tools and techniques. These include maintaining a dialog with the customer and quality assurers throughout the development process, building and releasing vertical slices incrementally, developing testing strategies, writing my code test-first, refactoring both test and production code, and using an automated continuous integration and deployment pipeline.

I believe that continuous improvement is crucial, both for development teams and for myself personally, and I enjoy working in teams that have the same ethos.

Primarily I've coded in C# but I am also experienced in building single page applications in Javascript using the AngularJS. I've written some Python and I've even started to learn a little Ruby.

## **Personal Development**

I am committed to my own personal development and I find there are so many interesting subjects within the industry. I've usually got a technical book on the go (currently 'RabbitMQ in Action') and attend events in London's thriving development community.

I've been a regular attendee of XProLo meetup, it's predecessor Extreme Tuesday Club and the associated conference XPDay as well as the London Software Craftsmanship meetups, favouring the hands-on sessions these days over talks. Recently I've started attending PaaS meetups, excited by the possibilities such platforms can bring to the development build and release process. I'm also interested in machine learning and data science.

I continue to use pet projects and code katas to learn new technologies and improve my technical skills.

## **Work Experience**

## Energyhelpline.com, Southwark, London

#### Jan 2011 - Present : Analyst Developer to Senior Developer

When I was looking for a new role after WTG I looked specifically for a company that could offer me freedom over my personal development process, particularly with respect to writing tests first and working in an agile manner. Energyhelpline.com fitted the bill.

I worked on and delivered some of energyhelpline's most important and successful projects over the last few years. Firstly, a RESTful energy comparison and switching API, relied on by Compare the Market and Go Compare, and subsequently a rebuild of our own publicly facing site to use that API using AngularJS, <a href="https://www.energyhelpline.com">www.energyhelpline.com</a>.

I developed more of an understanding and appreciation for application architecture gaining experience working with the CQRS+ES architectural patterns. With this knowledge, and that of object oriented design, test driven development and the REST architectural style, I've been acting as a de-facto lead developer for the team for the last year, supporting other developers with their design and architectural decisions.

I improved the speed and accuracy of development by cultivating a truly test driven culture within the team, introducing automated deployments, continuously improving the deployment pipeline, and developing testing strategies.

I changed the culture of the team through supporting others to learn and also through recuitment. I brought a new recruiter on board who understood our needs, I changed the messaging in our job specifications, got the team to silicon milkroundabout, and started a tech blog to improve our visibility to the development community.

I was lucky enough to work with some good developers at Energyhelpline.com, and there is no doubt that I'm a better programmer for it.

## WTG Technologies Ltd, Hammersmith, London

#### Nov 2007 - Jan 2012 : Junior C# Developer to Tech Lead

I worked on several projects, ending up as technical lead on a web application to aid the police with collaboration called POLKA. I also worked on DORS, a web application to enable people who had committed driving offenses to register for training schemes, and part of a multi-million pound solution to deliver a content managed help and information site for the 2011 UK Census.

I started my journey towards becoming a better, more fully engaged developer at WTG and implementing and evangelising about XP practices and techniques to improve the quality of our code and projects. The unit tests I wrote were the first units tests I'd written and the first written on the projects I worked on. I set up a continuous integration server, automated deployments, and tried, with limited success, to get my team mates pairing.

I managed to add an element of agility to the projects I worked on, particularly POLKA, by asking for work items to be prioritised enabling more important funcationality to be deilvered sooner, and having a member of the clients team work with us at our office one day a week, increasing the speed with which we could deliver working features by reducing the lag between communication and the accuracy of our work by improving the quality of the communication between the developers and the client.

### E3Media Ltd, Bristol

#### Aug 2006 - Nov 2007: Freelance Tester to Junior C# Developer

During two week's unpaid work experience as a manual tester I asked for some development work, the completion of which went some way to convincing them to hire me as a developer.

I worked on public facing websites for big multinationals such as Triumph motorcycles, Kia cars, and Orange, using the .NET stack. We didn't have much of a development process apart from hacking things out, but a colleague did lend me a book on XP sowing the seeds of my future development.

## Sharkbite Surf Shop, Bristol

#### Feb 2005 - Oct 2005 : Shop Assistant to Web Developer

I managed to negotiate a day a week out of the shop to design and build a small e-commerce site in Classic ASP. This gave me my first taste of production development and enough skills to land some work experience at E3Media.

## In My Own Time

When I'm not staring at a screen I'm fairly active. I do a bit of skateboarding even though I'm old enough to know better, some very amateur surfing, and I'm currently the captain of Coolhurst's 7th men's tennis team, looking forward to playing in Middlesex East Division 7 Summer League this summer, after three straight promotions.

## **Security Clearance**

SC Security Clearance - Lapsed

## **Education**

University of Bristol (2003 - 2004) MSc Computer Science

Liverpool John Moores (1997 - 2000) BA (hons.) Business Administration

The Woodroffe School, Lyme Regis (1992 - 1997) A-Levels and GCSEs